A Guide to the Powell-Drewry Family Papers, 1828-1934
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Powell-Drewry Family Papers, 1828-1934
Library of Virginia
37124, 37775, 42550
1.8 cubic feet
Powell-Drewry Families
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1 February 2000 and 31 October 2000.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Powell family were prominent residents of Henrico County, Virginia. Dr. John Norment Powell (1804-1874) was born in Westmoreland County, Virginia, and received his medical degree from the University of Pennsylvania. He married Mary Catherine Wright (1824-1885), also of Westmoreland County, on 1 February 1842 in Richmond County, Virginia. Afterwards, they resided at "Melrose," in Henrico County, northwest of Richmond, Virginia. They had three children: Junius Levert Powell (1843-1925), John J.A. Powell (1846-1930), and Blanche Norment Powell (1849-1909). Blanche married John William Drewry (d. 1873) on 7 November 1867. They had three children: William Powell Drewry (1868-1912), Mary Katherine Drewry (1870-1934), and Mildred Lee Drewry (b. 1872).
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1828-1934 (bulk 1860-1885), of the Powell and Drewry families of Fluvanna and Henrico Counties, and Richmond, Virginia. The bulk of the collection covers the years 1860 to 1885. The collection consists mainly of letters to Blanche Norment Powell Drewry (1849-1909), as well as Bible records, genealogical notes, clippings, a list of slaves, a portion of a diary, and a scrapbook.
The majority of this collection are letters written by various members of the Powell and Drewry families to Blanche N. Drewry. Correspondents include Charlotte Drewry Coalter, Augustus Henry Drewry, Clay Drewry, John William Drewry, William Powell Drewry, Sue T. Mayo, Annie S. Powell, John Norment Powell, Junius Levert Powell, Mary C. Powell, Rupert Powell, Ellen D. Smith, Maria L. Smith, Mary M. Smith, Clara M. Tuggle, and Elizabeth M. Walker.
Subjects covered in the early letters include Blanche's education at St. Mary's School in Raleigh, North Carolina, and Petersburg Female College in Petersburg, Virginia. There are a number of letters from her parents giving her encouragement and advice on schoolwork, manners, and habits, and expressing their concern over her health, as well as safety during the Civil War. Much of the correspondence details events of the war, including battles fought, troop movements, personal opinions, deaths of relatives and acquaintances who served, as well as her brother Junius' service in the Signal Corps. The post-war correspondence includes family news, births, marriages, and deaths of friends and acquaintances, social news, letters of sympathy concerning the deaths of her husband and her mother, and information on Junius Powell's service in the U.S. Army.
Also included are copies of Bible records of the Bronaugh and Drewry families, a copy of the will of Mary C. Powell, a copy of a list of slaves belonging to Dr. John N. Powell in 1861, a copy of a portion of a diary kept by Blanche N. Drewry covering the period 14 January through 3 February 1862, genealogical notes on the Bronaugh family, clippings, obituaries, and a small scrapbook.
Accession 37775 includes fourteen letters covering the years 1862 to 1864, envelopes, two receipts, and clippings. Also includes a plantation journal, 1862-1868, belonging to Mary C. Powell containing receipts, inventories of household goods and clothing, poetry, and clippings. This accession has been interfiled into Accession 37124.
Arrangement
Arranged into the following two series: I. Letters, 1828-1934, n.d.; II. Miscellaneous Papers.
Contents List
- Letters, 1828-1934, n.d. (Box 1-3)
  Dated letters are arranged chronologically. Undated letters are arranged alphabetically by last name of author.
  - 1828-1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1860 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1861 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1862 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1863 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1864 (January-May) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1864 (June-December) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1865 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1866 (January-April) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1866 (May-September) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1866 (October-December) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1867 (January-April) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1867 (May-August) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1867 (September-December) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1868 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1869 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1870 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1871 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1872 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1873 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1874 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1875 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1876 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1877 (January-June) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1877 (July-December) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1878 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1879 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1880-1884 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1885 (February) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1885 (March) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1886-1899 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1900-1905 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1906-1907 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1908-1909 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1910-1915, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Drewry, John William, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Drewry, Mary Harrison, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Mayo, Sue T., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Powell, Dr. John Norment, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Powell, Dr. Junius Levert, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Powell, Mary C., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Smith, Ellen D., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Smith, Maria L., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Smith, Mary M., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Tuggle, Clara M., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Various Individuals, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Miscellaneous Papers (Box 4)
  - Bronaugh Family Bible Record, 1730-1915 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bronaugh Family Genealogical Notes (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Drewry-Bronaugh Family Bible Record, 1824-1906 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Diary of Blanche Powell Drewry (copy), 14 January-3 February 1862 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Will of Mary C. Powell (copy), 1884 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - List of Slaves, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Clippings (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Envelopes (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
  - Postage Stamps (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - School Compositions (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Unidentified Photograph (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Plantation Journal, 1862-1868 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook (Box 4, Folder 16)